Cedric was obviously part of the school when I was a student.
So really my contact with Cedric came about as a student.
He was in the building a lot. He was no longer teaching.
He was involved in a number of high profile projects.
So he redesigned the South Bank for instance and so on.
He did a project for the South Bank and so on.
But he was a character. He was a friend of Alvin's. He came to Jury's.
So basically the wit and intelligence that Cedric had was something that you
experienced firsthand.
It wasn't, I mean, it would be wrong to say he didn't play to the gallery.
I think like Peter Cook, he was a character who played to the gallery.
So whenever he spoke, he wanted the room to be listening.
But I think he was also an incredible intelligence.
So he would react to what you said or what was actually put in front of him.
So my first meetings with him were always at juries.
So he was there.
He was pampered and spoilt by Alvin.
So there's famous stories, you know, he'd be given a cigar as he came in
and a bottle of brandy would appear under his chair
and he would sit there and just fill his glass up and talk.
So there were in those days quite a number of high profile juries as it were,
where people came from outside and so on, and you know,
you as one as a student went to all these things to see what was said.
And I think right from first year, I think going to these public juries,
you suddenly realise that Cedric was something that someone who you would go home
and ponder about what he said.
And I think what was always really important was that he never said anything in an
academic way.
He never said anything like a sort of professor or a teacher.
He would sort of remark on something.
It's rare to meet someone in the architectural environment in particular who is
willing to talk about private things.
You know, I think architects are quite facade-like.
you know they wear black and they do this and they behave in a particular way and
they only talk
about design um and i i think you know me personally you know i talk about fishing
and
football and so on you know i mean i i i think you know we are all human and i think
cedric
excelled at that he he he was a person who you felt warmth towards and i think he
also felt
warmth and admiration which i think is part of this friendship because you were
sharing
and understanding of what was around you,
not simply because you were sort of architects
who were being sort of portrayed.
Yeah, I think the uniqueness
was actually the level of sort of invention
and imagination that he could bring to the conversation,
a level of unpredictability,
a level of easy intelligence.
So in many ways,
when I say that a lot is written
and said and a lot is quoted and you know they're the archive of his tapes and I go
to all these
things and I thoroughly enjoy them I don't I'm not not complaining about them but in
a way I think
maybe the sign of friendship and this relationship that I'm talking about meant that
he would say
something to you you you'd go home and think about it and then you'd forget what he
said
so in a sense that's what what the true sign of you know someone actually affecting
you in one
way or another was really about which wasn't ah I've got a quote you know he said
this or he did
that or he made a reference. It was pretty much a capacity to see what you were
trying
to do, to understand where you were coming from and then to actually add something
which
possibly was well beyond what you had thought the possibilities were. And I think
that made
it very important. He was a sort of extraordinary Englishman. I think that there
were a series
of extraordinary Englishmen that affected me when I was young and when I was a
student.
I think John Somersom was one, Bob Evans was another one and Cedric was there. They
were
all three completely different men. Somersom was the grandee, old gentleman and
carer of
the CERN museum and so on and he came in his bicycle and his amazing tweed suits and
so
Bob was a wonderful family man, working-class boy, plastic bag full of books and so
on.
And Cedric summed them both up in a funny way.
So even the way Cedric looked was extraordinary.
He looked like a politician in a sense, with his hairstyle.
He looked like an old-fashioned Englishman with his thing all pulled back and his
cigar.
And then the stiff collar, the black silk tie, and the striped shirt, and then the
hush
puppy shoes, you know, brothel creepers underneath.
I mean, it's sort of complete.
He was a mixture between, I suppose, the foot area was like a sort of geography
teacher,
the trousers were like school uniform, and the top was like a sort of bowler hat
city
person.
And then in this extraordinary persona, you know, who used to come into a room, this
incredible
intelligence would come out.
So I think that he was unique, really unique.
I mean, unique even to look at.
In a sense he was, you know, his hair was always come back with sort of hair gel and
you know, et cetera, et cetera.
And in many ways, I think, in a world of delirious New York, Manhattan transcripts,
the things
which were happening.
I mean, Bernard Chewmey was red-scarfed already.
He would never be seen without it.
Nigel Coates, who then came to teach me how to have his glasses and looked the part.
He was a fashion person.
And Cedric was an anachronism.
And I think that made him stand out a lot
because I think a lot of the things I then went on to do
had this Englishness that I'm talking about,
this sort of slight eccentricity.
So when we moved on to do NATO,
when I was in diploma school,
when I was in Dip 10 and so on,
it was all kind of old-fashioned shirts
with the collar done up and old coats.
and, you know, it was sort of some weird mixture
back to the 40s with sort of punk.
And I'm not saying he was punk,
but I'm just simply saying he was quite extraordinary
in that sense, you know,
between the sort of studio jacket, the stiff collar.
The stiff collar, you see, the stiff collar,
I'm still sort of bewildered by that.
I mean, I don't know if he ever wore a stiff collar,
but they are really quite unpleasant.
And he had one every day, and his tie on every day.
So, you know, I think he was quite a striking figure within the whole process of
what I was seeing at the AA.
I think the other thing which was important is what I said before,
that I never got from Cedric this sense of an academic pretention or trajectory.
So with Somerson, he was a great scholar and he was an absolutely charming man.
with Bob Evans in his own quiet way,
he'd invite you around for tea.
He was a true friend.
I mean, I'd go to his house for tea and so on.
You've got a sense, you know,
God, this man's read all this and he's amazing
and he's teaching in Cambridge and he's written this
and he's written this essay.
With Cedric, you never got that.
Somehow, you didn't think, is he a great architect?
You sort of didn't decide.
Is he a great draftsman?
He was a good drawer, actually.
You sort of think, yeah,
but would I do lots of drawings of little ants?
He drew people everywhere, which is great.
I used to love that.
Every other architect did some pretentious sort of view.
Is he a great writer?
In a way, there was one book on Cedric
that was published in those days,
but it's great.
You've sort of read up about his projects and so on,
his seminal projects.
I think that the other thing that's important to point out
is a lot of people say that this,
when I was a student in the 70s
well late 70s and 80s you know a lot of people referred to this as the heyday of the
AA. Well
it wasn't. It wasn't sort of presented in that way. You didn't feel that. It was
just a smaller
place and there were some quite interesting people around. And it was more of a
focus for
practitioners than it is now. So the bar was the bar. I mean people would come and
hang around in
the bar and you'd meet you know famous architects as it were in the bar um but it
wasn't a sort of
you know a place it never had the sort of sense of of of what i think i can only
think so i've
never been to in that environment but you know it didn't have that sense of a sort
of an american
university where the great professor walks in you know and then therefore you know
everybody has to
sit up and listen it wasn't the aa was this sort of place where debates took place
and people came
because it was a fun thing to do.
Cedric came, I think he had a great time.
He didn't come here to pontificate, as I said.
I think he came here because he liked the discussion.
And, you know, so much so that I think the Cedrics
and the like in those days came to the parties.
So we had lots of parties.
You know, I think 1977 when I came
was the first AA carnival since the 40s
or maybe even pre-war.
So there was this big party, you know, 2,500 people,
and there was a trapeze artist across Chinx Yard,
and, you know, there were custard fights in the bar and so on.
You know, Cedric and people like Cedric would come to those parties.
It was a sort of different atmosphere, I think.
So I don't think it was that, you know, that the AA attracted him.
I think the AA was his sort of gravitational point,
and he was part of that process.
There is a key relationship between what I call physical and social structures,
i.e. that space is made up of the relationship between those two things.
So therefore I think the Fun Palace sort of in a sense sums that up.
It suggests the idea that space is never just a space that gets inhabited.
So it's a bit like the comment I was saying about the AA.
The AA didn't exist and Cedric came to it.
The AA and Cedric were one.
So I think it begins to suggest that. I think in the sort of bit that I don't think
is so relevant
is the idea of flexibility. I think another one that people look at is the idea of
performance
or event. I don't think that's so interesting either. I think it's much more to do
with the
idea of seeing something working, that has people in it. It's a sort of social
structure that works
with a physical structure. I think that's very interesting. I think that the
Thinkbelt project
is also interesting for that reason. It's talking about a system, you know, it's
actually talking about education in a different way and that's terrific. So
that is interesting to me today because I think maybe architects should be
thinking at that level. A lot of architects are thinking on a very banal
level of, you know, still form-making even though, you know, it's not talked about
at this very day, you know, on whatever it is today, the 8th of May 2014.
I think there's still an obsession with this making of objects.
And I think both of those, of Cedric's projects,
were basically not really talking about the object.
They were talking about the relationship of the object
to the context within which they sat.
And that context was actually a social context,
an economic context, and a political context.
I think that in terms of the grittiness of how the projects were presented,
I think that that light-hearted attitude that he had, which I mentioned before,
possibly would be out of place today,
because someone would make those two projects a lot more sort of theorising,
political, strong.
they'd be saying, no, no, this is the equivalent of the open university and so on.
Whereas Cedric was, again, in that playfulness,
actually suggesting things that foretold the future.
Yes, I think Cedric's emphasis on enabling, I think, is very, very important.
I think, possibly, it's something that he never articulated
beyond the realm of architecture.
and I think it's something that is very close to my heart.
So I think the idea of an architect not simply being a sort of form maker
or an object maker is very, very important.
So, but as far as my experience with Cedric was concerned,
I never really saw him becoming sort of involved at the bigger scale of urbanism
or the bigger scale of politics or at the bigger scale of sort of the,
politics that govern the making of space. It's not a conversation I ever had with
him or ever heard him talk about. So he did do these big projects for instance
he did the project for the South Bank where he kind of sort of he created
these whole new spaces you know the whole thing became much more of a public
space. But whether he was saying something about the politics of London
or about cities and so on I'm not so sure. So I think enabling he was he was
very intelligent about the idea that an architect doesn't have to resort to object
making. So I
think that was his vision of enabling and I think maybe everything that he did
including his funny
stories of let's say dinner with plates that you could see through to the floor and
so on you know
all these were like I think this is there's some some some extraordinary thing that
he did I think
he served food with see-through plates so that people could see their knees while
they were
eating on a glass table, you know, and it was all laid out. I think there's a video
actually of it,
so that, you know, when you finished eating your course you could then see your
knees and everybody
else's knees on the table, you know, and he sort of, he thought that was amusing,
you know. But I
think, you know, that's a really architectural project in a sense, you know, so I
think he was
doing it all the time, but I think his enabling was of a particular scale. I think
it wasn't that
enabling of that on the one hand is fashionable of alternative practice, you know, I
don't think
he was into that at all. I think what he was just simply saying is that the
strictures of what an
architect is are not sacred, were not sacred, and therefore that's why he worked in
his manner. And
I think actually a lot of his actions, as I was saying before, his being there, were
just as
critical in his making of what his world was than the actual things he was drawing
or writing upon.
I think where it's difficult to pin it down is that I think a lot of people were
quite political
at the time, you know, quite social at the time. Cedric wasn't. I mean, I'm not so
clear as to
what his position was.
You know, again, he was an extraordinary guy.
You know, he was sort of...
looked sort of like a conservative who was an artist,
if you see what I mean, in terms of his physical appearance
and the way he talked.
But actually, his political leadings?
Harder to point out.
Now, I think the other thing that's important
in terms of the deflation that Rem talks about.
I mean, he was an enfant terrible.
I mean, he was a provocateur.
So, you know, that was delightful.
That was great.
You know, and as I said before,
I don't think he took himself that seriously,
but he probably did, but didn't.
So I think he was very good
at taking the sort of pretension
that architects could put onto something
out of the room.
Definitely, delight was part of his agenda.
I mean, he was a happy bloke.
in fact actually I think the last time I
I saw Cedric I was
quite upset actually he was
old and he
I can't remember there was sort of an exhibition
near my office near John Street near
Guilford Street where my office is and I walked
over after the office and I saw him in there and he was
he was pretty gone I mean he was
old and so on and Eleanor was sort of getting him in and out
of a taxi and so on.
And it was a very sad thing to see.
I mean, obviously,
it's going to happen to all of us.
So I'm not thinking
we're going to get away with it.
But it was sad
because actually Cedric
was beaming all the time.
You know, he was a happy bloke.
Like I say, I never saw him angry.
I mean, I said earlier
that I didn't see him passionate.
He was passionate.
You know, he would argue his corner,
but always with humour and lightness.
So I think, yes,
delight was partly there.
And maybe, you know,
Rem is again right about that.
I think delight was something
that architects weren't so used to expressing when Cedric was around.
People took themselves quite seriously, in a sense.
So I think Peter Cook was sort of famous
while I was a student for being a sort of architect of delight.
He was interested in Japan and he'd made friends with Isozaki
and he talked about layers in Tokyo and so on.
But again, you see, he had a great sense of humour about it,
but it was all very structured.
Cedric Walson, I think Cedric actually did enjoy
getting up in the morning and doing his own thing.
And as I said, I think some people
had very close relationships with him,
and I think they obviously,
they were enjoyable relationships.
They were never sycophantic,
something we discussed earlier.
I think they enjoyed his company.
He was fun to be with, and I think he enjoyed things.
He enjoyed drawing. He enjoyed architecture.
he enjoyed learning, he enjoyed being here and so on.
So yes, I think so, and I think maybe that is something that he's left as a legacy
to quite a number of people, to actually just take architecture off its pedestal
and see it in a different way.
I think it's a very important role, but I would also say that it's also a live role.
I think that somehow to think that Cedric was the only character who could do that
is problematic.
I think in a sense there probably are some Cedrics around.
They certainly won't be called Cedric.
It's an extraordinary name.
But there are probably some Cedrics around that should equally be given opportunity
to informally have a tremendous influence on what's happening.
And again, Cedric was always, just to use the pun, priceless at doing that.
Because he was always with the big players, but he was never a big player.
So he was there with every world architect.
and what had he built?
You know, it's a sort of, you know,
if you were going to compare, you know, CVs,
how much did he earn?
You want to compare CVs, you know,
but there he was, he was always a player
and I think maybe in a sense,
it's not that there are no Cedrics now,
I think it's that maybe we don't allow enough Cedrics
into the conversation as we used to.
I think the whole education,
the whole Englishness that I was talking about,
the system of individuality,
which was absolutely critical,
after the war years, you know, in terms of education and so on, has now changed.
I think it's more process based and happening elsewhere.
So, you know, I think
to me, even though I'm not an Englishman,
he was the epitome of an Englishman
and of a system that allowed the free thinker.
Now, some people were very critical of that and would say, you know,
that's being a dilettante or being, you know, sort of not focused enough.
but I think in a way that that worries me so I think no legacy or no evolution of
what Cedric
was doing is possible unless you allow the maverick thinker to exist again and I
think that's
difficult at the moment I'm not saying it won't change but I think it's things the
conditions
have changed so I think his his legacy is what he did and maybe what you guys are
doing and
what the books will say. But I think my urge towards the future is that I would
have thought he would have wanted you to piece the pieces together in whichever
way you thought fit, rather than the way that they should go together.